Hello.
안녕하세요.
In this session, I'd talk about the kernel hacking for signal tracing.
이번 세션에서는 커널 해킹하여 시그널을 추적하는 것에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
My name is Leesoo Ahn. and I am currently working as an engineer at a wireless router company.
제 이름은 안이수라고 하고요 현재 무선공유기 회사에서 엔지니어로 일하고 있습니다.
I worked as a contributor at GNONE for 2 years from 2018, and I am currently conducting research related to the kernel.
2018년부터 2년간 GNONE에서 컨트리뷰터로 활동했고 현제는 커널과 관련된 연구를 진행하고 있습니다.
I'm sure some of you here already know about Signals.
아마 여기 계신 분들은 이미 시그널에 대해 알고 계실 거예요.
Signals are one of many inter-process communications that currently exist in Linux
시그널은 현재 리눅스에 존재하는 많은 Inter-process communication 중의 하나 인데요
To give a simple example, here are two processes: a parent and a child.
간단한 예제를 보여드리자면 여기 부모와 자식 두 개 프로세스가 있습니다.
The parent is sending a message to the child, and this overall picture is IPC.
부모가 자식에게 메시지를 전달하고 있는데 이 전체적인 그림이 IPC이고요.
And the message be used in here is Signal.
그리고 거기에 사용되는 메시지가 바로 Signal입니다.
Of course, children can also respond to their parents.
물론 자식도 부모에게 응답할 수 있지만.
It only depends on how the child program is implemented.
그건 오로지 자식 프로그램이 어떻게 구현되어 있는가에 따라 달라져요.
The situation in the previous example is often what we see in textbooks.
앞 예시에 나온 상황은 흔히 우리가 텍스트북에서 보던 내용이죠.
It seems to have no problems and it looks fine, but...
문제도 없고 괜찮아 보이지만
There are more complicated situations than these happy situations in actual production.
프로덕트에서는 이렇게 행복한 상황보다는 복잡한 상황이 더 많이 발생해요.
For example, there are cases where completely unrelated processes send a signal to their children,
예를 들면 전혀 상관없는 프로세스들이 자식에게 시그널을 보내는 경우도 있고,
and there may be situations where the parent does not receive the signal.
부모가 보낸 시그널을 받지 못하는 상황도 생길 수 있어요.
When we face a issue related in signals, it can be easily solved if you know how to analyze it,
시그널과 관련된 문제가 생겼을 때에 분석하는 방법을 알면 손쉽게 해결할 수 있는데
but how can we do it?
도대체 어떻게 해야 할까요?
Several tools are available to analyze these problems.
몇 가지 툴을 이용해서 이러한 문제점들을 분석할 수 있어요.
The first is a tool you know. GDB is a line-by-lline debugger, and
첫 번째는 여러분들이 아는 툴인데요 GDB는 line-by-lline 디버거이고
you can attach it to a process, and you can check the currently running statement line-by-line.
프로세스에 Attach하면 현재 실행 중인 부분을 line-by-line으로 확인할 수 있어요.
Also, we can use Strace. Strace is lighter than GDB,
그 다음은 Strace 인데 Strace 같은 경우에는 GDB 보다 경량화 되어 있고
and it is designed to focus in only System-calls and signals in our tracings.
System-call과 시그널만 트레이싱 할 수 있도록 설계 되었어요.
Third, we have Ftrace. Unlike GDB and Strace, Ftrace can trace system-wide and can analyze most events occurring in the kernel.
세 번째는 Ftrace라고 하는 툴인데요 Ftrace는 GDB와 Strace와는 다르게 시스템 전역적으로 트레이스가 가능하고 커널에서 발생하는 대부분의 이벤트에 대해 분석이 가능해요.
There must be many other techniques that I am not aware of.
그 외에 제가 모르는 테크닉들이 많이 있겠죠?
But if
그런데 만약에
the situation I showed you earlier happens
앞에 보여 드렸던 이 상황이
when the system is booting up, there are more things to consider.
시스템이 부팅 할 때 발생한다면 고려해야 할게 더 많아 지거든요.
Tools such as GDB, Strace, and Ftrace are stored in the file system, but if the file system is being mounted at the time the problem occurs, we can't use them, plus,
GDB나 Strace, Ftrace 같은 툴들은 파일시스템 내에 저장되어 있는데 문제가 발생하는 시점에 해당 파일 시스템이 마운트 중이라면 사용하지 못하고요.
The order of execution between the target process and the debuggers should also be considered.
타겟 프로세스와 디버거들 간의 실행 순서도 고려를 해야 돼요.
For example, if we run the debuggers first before the target is executed, analysis wouldn't be made, right?
예를 들면 타겟이 실행 되기 전에 디버거들을 먼저 실행시키게 되면 분석이 불가능하겠죠?
Furthermore, in embedded systems, shell access is blocked for security, and we couldn't launch a debugger through a terminal, in such environments.
또한 임베디드 시스템에서는 보안을 위해 쉘 접근을 막아 놓는데 이러한 환경인 경우에 터미널을 통해 디버거를 실행하는게 불가능하겠죠.
Besides that, there are a few other things to consider.
그 외에도 몇 가지 고려를 해야 하는 게 있을 거고요.
We know it isn't the core of the problem, but It forces us focus to such tiresome tasks, so it's so stressful and annoying.
문제 그 본질도 아니고 다른 부분에 에너지를 쏟아야 하니까 머리도 아프고 너무 귀찮아요.
Rather than that, it would be better to focus on the original problem and finish it quickly, right?
그러지 말고 원래 본질적인 문제에만 빨리 집중해서 끝내는게 좋겠죠?
If it is correct to modify the code to solve this problem, wouldn't it be more efficient to access and analyze the signal handling routines in the kernel?
이 문제를 해결하기 위해 코드를 수정하는게 맞다면 커널에 있는 시그널 처리 루틴에 접근해서 분석하는게 더 효율적이지 않을까요?
I approached to it with this thinking.
저는 이렇게 생각해서 접근하게 되었고요.
Again, there are two processes here, and the parent is sending a signal to the child. It is a view of signal processing in user level.
다시 여기에 두 개 프로세스가 있고 부모가 자식한테 시그널을 보내고 있어요 이는 유저 레벨에서 본 시그널이 처리되는 과정이고요
and it is the kernel level view in practice.
실제로 커널은 이와 같아요.
The parent requests a signal from the kernel through the 'kill' system-call, and the kernel handles taken signal, and delivers it to the child.
부모는 Kill System-call을 통해 커널에게 시그널을 요청하고 커널은 시그널을 처리하여 자식에게 전달하게 되죠.
If this kernel level is further subdivided, it can be divided into three stages as follows.
이 커널 레벨을 좀 더 세분화 해보면 다음처럼 스테이지 세 개로 나눌 수가 있고요.
Of the three stages, we will edit the code in stage-3.
세 개의 스테이지 중에 스테이지-3에서 코드를 수정 할 거예요.
You may be thinking, 'There are three stages, so why am I going to edit in stage 3?' The first reason is related in security.
'세 개의 스테이지가 있는데 왜 하필 스테이지 3에서 수정을 할까'라고 생각하실 수 있고요 그 첫 번째 이유로는 보안과 관련이 있어요.
The kernel must always handle an exception for the value sent by the users.
커널은 사용자가 보내는 값에 대해 항상 예외 처리를 수행 해야 되는데요,
For example, the users can pass an invalid integer to the kernel rather then signal number, so it must always be checked.
예를 들면 사용자는 시그널 번호가 아닌 다른 정수값을 커널에게 전달할 수 있기 때문에 항상 확인을 해야 돼요.
Secend we should check the process, which is to make sure that the
두 번째는 프로세스를 확인해야 하는데요,
target is alive on the current system.
타겟이 현재 시스템에 살아 있는지 확인하는 작업이고요.
If the process does not exist, there is no need to handle the signal.
해당 프로세스가 없다면 굳이 시그널을 처리할 필요가 없겠죠.
Also, if there are multiple threads in one process, you need to check which thread to send to.
또한 하나의 프로세스의 쓰레드가 여러 개 있는 경우 어떤 쓰레드에 전달할 건지도 확인해야 하고요.
Then, you have to check for null pointers at the code level,
코드 레벨에서는 Null pointer를 체크해야 하고,
and there must be many other things such as security.
그 외에도 시큐리티 관련 이라든지 여러가지 사항들이 있겠죠.
Now we understand the reason for doing it in stage 3, but how should we fix it?
스테이지 3에서 하는 이유는 알겠는데 그럼 어떤 방식으로 수정을 해야 할까요?
In a nutshell, first, we will filter out all signals that is unnecessary in tracing.
간단하게 살펴보면 첫 번째로는 트레이싱이 필요 없는 시그널은 전부 필터링 할 거예요.
By printk, we'll output the results to a console.
printk를 이용해서 콘솔로 출력을 할 거고요.
In the content, the process name and PID in the Sender, the process name and PID in the Receiver, and the signal number are output.
내용에는 Sender에 프로세스 이름과 PID, Receiver에 프로세스 이름과 PID, 그리고 시그널 번호를 출력하고요.
This is a simple patch I made based on the information we looked at earlier
이는 앞서 살펴본 정보를 바탕으로 만든 간단한 패치인데요
I modified it to filter SIGCHLD and SIGALRM and output Sender and Receiver and signal numbers.
저는 SIGCHLD와 SIGALRM을 필터링하고 Sender와 Receiver, 그리고 시그널 번호를 출력하도록 수정했어요.
This is the Kernel call stack executed when the 'kill' system-call is called,
이 내용은 Kill System-call이 호출 되었을 때 실행되는 Kernel call stack 이고요,
and after processing stages 1 and 2, it is adjusted to output after complete_signal is completed in the send_signal function.
스테이지 1과 2를 처리하고 난 뒤에 send_signal 함수 내에 complete_signal이 완료되고 나서 출력하도록 조정하였습니다.
From now on, I will show you briefly using the system to which the aforementioned patch is applied.
그럼 지금부터 앞서 설명드린 패치를 적용한 시스템을 이용하여 간단하게 보여 드리도록 하겠습니다.
This terminal is currently connected to the Raspberry Pi.
이 터미널은 현재 라즈베리파이에 연결되어 있고요.
Currently doing a reboot.
현재 재부팅을 수행하고 있고.
We will continue to explain after booting.
부팅 후에 계속 설명드리도록 하겠습니다.
Now the booting is complete, let's analyze the boot message slowly.
이제 부팅이 완료 되었는데요 천천히 부팅 메시지를 분석하도록 하겠습니다.
As we can see here, before the file system is initialized in the boot phase,
여기 보시는 바와 같이 부팅 단계에서는 8 시스템이 초기화되기 전에.
As the signal can be transmitted as shown above, it is difficult to use the tracing tool described above.
위에 나와 있는 것처럼 시그널이 전송될 수 있기 때문에 앞서 설명드린 트레이싱 툴을 사용하는 게 어려운 환경이고요.
If you hack the kernel and analyze it, you can easily check it like this.
커널을 해킹해서 분석하게 되면 이처럼 손쉽게 확인할 수 있습니다.
Again, here is a message that the file system is being initialized and a signal is sent before that, and then we will send a
여긴 다시 한 번 말씀드리지만 여기 파일 시스템이 초기화되고 있고 그 이전에 시그널이 전송되는 메시지이고요
signal through the kill command in the shell.
그 다음에 쉘에서 kill 명령어를 통해 시그널을 날리도록 하겠습니다.
Using this 'kill' command, I'm going to send a signal to the DHCP client,
이 kill 명령어를 이용을 해서 저는 DHCP 클라이언트한테 시그널을 보내도록 할 거고요
and now I'm going to send a signal using the command.
이제 명령어을 이용하여 시그널을 전달하도록 하겠습니다.
Then, as you can see in the kernel message, the Sender becomes the shell and the Reciever becomes the DHCP client in the shell.
그러면 커널 메시지에 보시는 바와 같이, 쉘에서 Sender는 쉘이 되는 거고 Reciever가 DHCP 클라이언트가 되는 거고요.
You can confirm that the SIGUSR1 signal is delivered through the message.
SIGUSR1 시그널이 전달되는 것을 메시지를 통해 확인을 할 수가 있습니다.
Next, I will show you how the signal works when rebooting through the reboot command.
그 다음에는 재부팅 명령어를 통해서 재부팅을 할 때에, 시그널이 어떤 방식으로 동작을 하게 되는지 보여 드리도록 하겠습니다.
I ran the reboot command.
재부팅 명령어를 수행을 했고요.
This will be
이는
explained when the reboot process is completed to some extent.
어느 정도 재부팅 프로세스가 완료가 되면 설명을 드리도록 하겠습니다.
The reboot is now almost complete.
현재 거의 재부팅이 완료가 된 상태구요.
I will explain the contents of the signal generated through the reboot command.
재부팅 명령어를 통해 나온 시그널 내용에 대해서 설명을 드리도록 하겠습니다.
First, when the reboot command is executed, a signal is sent to all processes in the current system.
우선은 재부팅 명령어를 수행하게 되면 현재 시스템에 있는 전체 프로세스에게 시그널이 전송이 되게 되고요.
In the case of number 15, it becomes the SIGTERM signal number.
15번 같은 경우에는 SIGTERM 시그널 번호가 되는 거고요.
In this way, when the process is completely terminated, a reboot is performed.
그렇게 해서 완전히 프로세스가 종료 하게 되면은 재부팅을 수행하게 됩니다.
Therefore, it is possible to analyze what kind of signals are invoked while rebooting through the kernel hacking.
따라서 커널을 해킹 하게 되면 재부팅을 하게 되면서 어떤 시그널이 날아가게 되는지 이런 한 것들도 분석을 할 수 있게 되고요.
So, let's finish the demo demonstration and go back to the presentation.
그래서 데모 시연은 이 정도로 해서 마치도록하고 다시 프레젠테이션으로 돌아가도록 하겠습니다.
In this session, rather than deeply analyzing the kernel, I explained from the point of view that there was a certain issue and it was solved by modifying the kernel to solve it.
이번 세션은 커널에 대해 깊게 분석하기 보다는 넓게 어떠한 이슈가 있었고 그걸 해결하기 위해 커널을 수정해서 해결했다는 관점으로 설명을 드렸어요.
I'm glad you've gotten even a little closer to the kernel,
여러분 들이 커널과 조금이라도 가까워지셨다면 다행이고요
and I'll end my presentation here.
제 발표는 여기에서 마치도록 하겠습니다.
Thank you!
감사합니다.